if you could introduce yourselves uh
yourself to our audience, your time in
uh Pakistan and what capacity you were
working in Pakistan and then eventually
your whistleblowing and then the sort of
vendetta that was unleashed against you
by the American intelligence setup and
where you are right now. Just a quick
introduction.
>> Sure. Sure. Thanks for that.
>> As you want.
>> Sure. Thank you. My name is John
Kiryaku. I'm a former CIA officer. I was
in the CIA for 15 years. Uh my the first
half of my career was in analysis. The
second half was in counterterrorism
operations. And um in 2007, I blew the
whistle on the CIA's torture program in
a nationally televised interview here in
the United States. I said that the CIA
was torturing its prisoners. I said that
torture was official US government
policy. And I said that the policy had
been personally approved by the
president. Um, the Obama administration,
[clears throat] excuse me, in the form
of John Brennan
went after me and they pursued criminal
charges. I was uh indicted on five
felony uh charges, including three
counts of espionage for saying that the
CIA was torturing its prisoners. Of
course, I hadn't committed espionage.
>> Um,
but um and those charges were dropped,
but I ended up serving 23 months in
prison. um something that I would do
again today if I had to. I have no
regrets, no remorse. I did the right
thing. And I think that we're seeing now
uh that I did the right thing. It took
the American people this long to come
around to my way of thinking that
torture is wrong. It's illegal and
should be punished. Um
the last overseas job that I had at the
CIA was um in 2002. I was the chief of
CIA counterterrorism operations in
Pakistan. Uh and this was the immediate
aftermath of the 9/11 attacks. And in
that position, my job was to um locate
al-Qaeda fighters and leaders and to uh
snatch them.
>> Well, I was based in Islamabad, but I
worked all over the country. Peshawar
all the way to uh to Karachi. I spent a
great deal of time in Lahore and
Fiselabad.
>> Uh Qua which was a a rough a rough place
to live and work. [clears throat] Excuse
me. But um yeah, I I finished that job
and went back to headquarters. I was
promoted on the strength of uh of my
work in Pakistan and I served as the
executive assistant to the CIA's deputy
director for operations. And so it was a
a real eye opening experience. Now I'm a
I'm a an author, a journalist. I've
written eight books. I have um two
podcasts. I I have uh two syndicated
newspaper columns. I speak all around
the world and you know things have
things have worked out. Thank god.
>> Uh your voice is an authoritative voice
because I mean you've been in the field.
uh you've seen geopolitics play out real
time especially in an area like
Pakistan. Uh you were also credited for
the first takedowns of I would think a
high value target of the al-Qaeda Abu
Abu Zubeda and then
>> Abu Zubeda
>> which eventually led to the actual
whistleblowing of torture techniques
used on him which uh didn't really work
out though. Can you explain how that
happened? How how did you nab him? And
then I'll go deeper into some other
questions I have about Pakistan and
terrorists in Pakistan.
>> Sure. You're right that Abu Zabeda was
the first high-value target that we were
able to to track and to find and to
capture. We believed wrongly at the time
that Abu Zabeda was the number three in
al-Qaeda. He was not the number three.
He had never joined al-Qaeda. He was he
was working in support of al-Qaeda.
Certainly,
>> he had founded the House of Martyrs, the
al-Qaeda safe house in Peshawar. He had
founded and staffed al-Qaeda's two
training camps in southern Afghanistan.
One in Kandahar, one in Helmund. Uh so
he was he was a bad guy, but he was not
the number three in al-Qaeda.
Nonetheless, we believed that he was. We
tracked his movements and we were close,
this close a couple of times to
capturing him. Finally, we we got a beat
on him because he made a mistake. We
knew that he would make a mistake
eventually, but he made a mistake in
that he used his cell phone to access
his email account.
>> Okay.
>> And and so when he turned the phone on,
we immediately
captured its location, we sent teams and
we we captured him. He was taken to a
series of secret prisons over the course
of the next uh four years and then
finally in 2006 he was taken to
Guantanamo. He's been there ever since.
>> Yeah.
>> He's been in American custody now for 23
and a half years. He's never been
charged with a crime. And
[clears throat] I've become one of those
voices
calling for him to be released. He was
not the number three in al-Qaeda. he was
not guilty of the crimes that we accused
him of uh having committed. He was not
involved with the 9/11 attacks. He
should be released and um and he's not
been and he likely won't be.
>> You know, I've heard this story of yours
uh in various podcasts and appearances
that you've done. One question that I
always wanted to ask you was this
sentiment that you have about Abu
Zubeda. Is it shared by I guess your
colleagues at that time at the Pakistan
I Pakistan's ISI cuz you were working
with them to uh to nab targets right?
>> Yeah but it was a little bit more
complicated than that.
Forgive me for saying this. You're
Indian of course you're not Pakistani
but we didn't fully trust the Pakistani
ISI at the time. So we never told them
who the target was.
>> Okay.
>> We we never said it's it's Abu Zuba
Zadin Muhammad.
>> I will take umbrage to that. That's
fine. [laughter]
>> Because we were afraid that word would
leak out and it would get back to
al-Qaeda.
And so we just called him a big fish.
>> Oh.
>> Which which became Mr. Fish. So we
believe that Mr. Fish is at this
location. Let's send teams and we're
going to we're going to snatch him. So
um the reason why we we believed that
the reason why we did that is because we
were of the belief
and in all these years of retrospect I
know that this is true that there really
were two parallel ISIS.
>> There was the the ISI that I was working
with and these guys were heroes. They
were all trained at Sandhurst in the UK.
They had taken classes in the US
sponsored by the FBI.
Their English was as good as mine.
Great guys who were willing to put their
lives on the line in the name of
counterterrorism.
But then there was another ISI
made up of people with long beards
>> who gave you a dirty look when you were
walking the halls there. These were the
members of ISI who had created
[clears throat]
these Kashmiri terrorist groups
or Ji Muhammad or you know other groups
that were blowing up Shia Muslim mosques
and were attacking Americans.
So we we did not have rosecolored
glasses on at the time thinking that
everybody in ISI is wonderful because
our relationship with the
counterterrorism units was wonderful.
You're right.
>> It was far more complicated than that.
>> [music]